Guide to the New York City Immigrant Labor History Project Oral History Collection OH.014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- New York City Immigrant Labor History Project
  - Opochinsky, Isidore, 1975 April 19 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 140, Box 46, Reel 155a - 155b, Box 1, Folder 65)
    Isidore Opochinsky was born in an unspecified European country (likely Hungary). He and his 11 siblings were taught by a rabbi in their home. Opochinsky attended high school in Europe. He immigrated to the United States (US) in 1921 and lived with his brother in New York, New York. He worked as a fur machine operator in both Hungary and the US. He was a member of an unspecified union in the US (likely the International Fur and Leather Workers Union) and was an executive board member of the national union and chairman of his local. In Europe, he was an active member of the General Jewish Labour Bund of Lithuania, Poland, and Russia; an unspecified Socialist party; and in the US, he participated in the Jewish Socialist movement.
    This interview was conducted by Gary Tilzer on April 19, 1975 at the Workmen's Circle Home for the Aged in the Bronx, New York. This interview covers Isidore Opochinsky's life in Hungary; his immigration to the United States (US) in 1921; his work as a fur machine operator in New York, New York; and his union activity. Opochinsky tends to mumble and is sometimes hard to understand. He provides few details about his childhood and early life in Europe, focusing on his involvement in the General Jewish Labour Bund of Lithuania, Poland, and Russia. He recalls that he learned of the importance of unionization and the tenets of Socialism through members of the Bund. He notes that members of the Bund who immigrated to the US had an easier time acclimating because they had the resources and social ties of an organized group. He explains that he worked without pay for six months while he trained in the fur industry in Europe. He recounts immigrating to the US in 1921, because he could not make a living in Europe after World War I, and settling with his brother in New York, New York. He explains that he returned to Europe after a conflict with an unspecified fur workers' union (likely the International Fur and Leather Workers Union). He discusses his return to the United States when he could not find work in Europe and his vow to rid the union of those in power who monopolized its funds and activities. He recalls neglecting his education and his family in order to reorganize the leadership of the union, noting that after his removal of the corrupt leaders, the resulting chaos provided an opportunity for the Communists gain power. He describes a strike that occurred in 1926, including the fact that it lasted 26 weeks; that the police killed many of the strikers; and that the strikers won, earning medical benefits and better hours and wages. Other topics include details of the work of the fur industry; a comparison of labor unions and living and working conditions in Europe and the US; and his attendance and involvement in an unspecified conference concerned with Jewish labor issues in Geneva, Switzerland.
    Jewish socialists -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews.; Labor unions -- Officials and employees -- United States.; Allgemeyner Idisher arbayṭerbund in Liṭa, Poylen un Rusland; Workmen's Circle (U.S.); International Fur and Leather Workers Union of the United States and Canada
  - Pane, Frank, 1975 April 30 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 170, Box 46, Reel 156a - 156b)
    Historical/Biographical Note
    Frank Pane was born on March 21, 1891 in Sorrento, Italy. He was one of ten children and attended an unnamed school in Sorrento and the Saint Charles School in New York, New York. His father was a longshoreman. Pane started working as a bookbinder after his father was injured at work. He worked in the printing department but also functioned as an intermediary between the predominantly Italian lithograph operators and management. He shifted to working as a ship caulker during World War II. He was a member of the International Longshoremen's Association.
    This interview was conducted on April 30, 1975 by John Jentz and Jay Facciolo at an unspecified location. In addition to Frank Pane, there is an unknown man who intermittently comments on the interviewers' questions. This interview covers Pane's childhood in Italy, his immigration to the United States, and his life and work as a bookbinder and longshoreman in New York, New York. Pane discusses his family history, noting the contrast between his father, who was a relatively poor longshoreman, and his mother, who had inherited two large homes from her parents. He recounts how his father's schooner was destroyed by a steamboat while at sea and how the steamboat crew, who were headed to the United States, brought him with them, and he settled in New York in order to acquire more job opportunities. Pane and the rest of his family immigrated to the United States later in 1898 via the ship Victoria. He describes the poor living conditions that many immigrants, including his family, endured. He notes that during the the depressions before and after World War I, Father Vogel at the Saint Charles Chapel on Van Brunt and President Streets in Brooklyn, New York would distribute food and coal tickets to poor families. He describes evading the draft during World War II in order to support his family and shifting his occupation from bookbinder to work as a caulker in the shipyards. He notes that he liked the work due to the outdoor environment, a stark contrast to the dirty factories that he had worked in as a bookbinder, but disliked the inconsistent employment. Pane emphasizes the politics of New York City, specifically the relationship between Democratic and Republican policies during the Great Depression. He ascribes the depressions of the early 20th century to the Republican administrations.
    Bookbinders |z United States |v Interviews.
  - Passage, Undated (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 242, Box 47, Reel 157a)
    This recording contains excerpts of interviews containing narrators' experiences of the immigration process. The volume and sound quality of the recording fluctuate between excerpts. The excerpts contain discussions of immigrants' journeys to the United States; their memories of Ellis Island; requirements for immigration; and the sequence of immigration in families.
    See also: Canossa, Bruno; Farkas, Bella; Fox, Abe; Robinson, Irene; Savio, Joseph; Sutton, Kathleen; and Ward, Katherine.
    Ellis Island (N.J. and N.Y.)
  - Pasternak, Morris and Florence, 1973 March 16 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 28-29, Box 47, Reel 158a - 158c, Box 1, Folder 66)
    Morris Pasternak was born in 1897 in a shtetl in Ukraine, Russia and was one of eight children. He immigrated to the United States in 1906 and lived in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. He attended the Hebrew Technical Institute and the Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art in Manhattan. He worked as a machinist in garages in Manhattan and as a chemist at the School of Mines of Columbia University. He joined the Socialist Party of America in 1918. He married Florence Pasternak in 1928.
    Florence Pasternak was born in Russia. She immigrated to the United States in 1913. Her father worked as a pants presser and was an active member of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America. She married Morris Pasternak in 1928.
    This interview was conducted on March 16, 1973 at the home of Morris and Florence Pasternak in Queens, New York by two unidentified interviewers. The majority of the interview features Morris Pasternak's interest in the history of the labor movement in the United States (US) and the Socialist Party of America, with interjections from his wife, Florence. He also discusses his early life in Ukraine, Russia; his education; and his working life in the US.
    Pasternak recounts his early life in a shtetl in Ukraine, including one of his older brothers mounting a defense in advance of a pogrom. He describes his development as a Socialist, including observing working conditions in the factories in which his brothers worked in Manhattan, New York; reading anarchist literature they brought home; and attending speeches by Emma Goldman with one of his brothers. Other topics include forced prostitution of Jewish immigrant women in New York City and Jewish organized crime.
    Socialists |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Politics, Undated (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 237, Box 47, Reel 159a)
    This recording contains excerpts of several interviews, all of which focus on discussions of politics in New York, New York. These excerpts cover the conflict between local landlords and city and state legislation regarding New York building codes; an unspecified church's view of and relationship with politics; the development and purpose of the American Labor Party; differences between the Democratic and Republican parties; and the relationship among different radical political groups in New York City. The narrators reflect on the policies and effectiveness of political figures -- including Fiorello La Guardia, Vito Marcantonio, James J. Walker, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and Marcus Garvey -- and the differences between politicians at the time of the interviews and in the past.
    See also: Geller, Bessie; Goldman, Sam and Dora Shapiro; Magliacano, Joseph; Sutton, Kathleen; Torres, Tony; and Unger, Margareta.
  - Prescant, Becky, 1973 March 26 (Box Missing, Box 1, Folder 102)
    Becky Prescant was born in a small town in Poland around 1894. She was one of six children. Her father was a tailor, and her mother was a seamstress. She attended a Jewish school in Poland, where she learned to read Hebrew. She immigrated to the United States (US) in 1912 when she was 17 years old and initially settled with her uncle's family on 7th Street and Avenue B in the East Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. She later moved to 103rd Street and Madison Avenue in the East Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan with her brother and sister-in-law. She married and had four children. She worked in the garment industry in ladies' waists, dresses, and piecework and was an active member of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU).
    This interview was conducted by Jon Saul at the Kingsbridge Heights Nursing Home in the Bronx, New York on March 26, 1973. The audio recording for this interview is missing. This interview covers Becky Prescant's childhood in Poland; her immigration to the United States (US) in 1912; and her work and union activity in the garment industry in New York, New York. Prescant describes her hometown in Poland, noting that although there was no open hostility between the Jewish people and other religious populations, the local school did not accept Jewish students. She recalls learning Hebrew at a Jewish school; learning how to sew at a local tailor shop; and working on the family farm. She explains that she chose to immigrate to the US because there were no Jewish men for her to marry and no doctors in her town. She mentions that some of her other siblings emigrated in order to avoid being drafted into the Russian Army or being persecuted for their belief in Socialism.
    Prescant describes immigrating to the US and settling in New York, New York in 1912, including how she pretended to be the daughter of another woman in order to leave Poland. She describes her initial surprise at the differences between Poland and the US, particularly in terms of architecture and food. She discusses her husband, including how they met and his death 12 years after their marriage. She describes her first job in a garment shop on the west side of Manhattan; the differences between garment shops in Poland and the US; and the brutal conditions in the shop in which she worked. She recounts her involvement in the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU); a four month strike in which she participated for better working conditions; and the tension between the strikers and the police. Other topics include the importance of religion to her family; the education and occupations of her children; and a comparison of both the ILGWU and her neighborhood in the past and at the time of the interview.
    See also: Ethnicity; Immigration, Migration, and First Impressions of New York, New York and the United States; Interview Compilation for Radio Broadcast; and Life Before Immigration or Migration.
    Jews, Polish -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews
  - Preuhs, Albert, 1974 April 23 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 251, Box 48, Reel 161a - 161b)
    Albert Preuhs was born in Hamburg, Germany on September 3, 1886. His father worked as a baker, eventually owning his own bakery. His mother worked in a kitchen for the city of Hamburg during an unspecified war but otherwise did not work outside the home. He attended school in Germany for eight years before moving into the workforce as a baker when he was 18 years old, joining a bakers' union in Hamburg. Preuhs served in the German merchant marine and the German Navy before he immigrated to the United States (US) in January 1911. He lived in the Beggars' Boarding House on 5th Street between 1st and 2nd Avenue in the East Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York before getting his own apartment. He worked as a baker and joined an unspecified bakers' union in New York (likely the Journeymen Bakers Union of New York).
    This interview was conducted by Scott Weir at the Stanley M. Isaacs Neighborhood Center in Manhattan, New York on April 23, 1974. This interview covers Albert Preuhs' childhood and early adult life in Germany; his immigration to the United States (US); and a summary of his life in New York, New York. Preuhs begins by describing his father's work in a bakery in Hamburg, Germany, noting his membership in a local union and his progression from employee to manager of his own business. He describes working as an apprentice for three years before traveling to various German cities during his time as a journeyman. Preuhs explains that he joined the German merchant marine in order to travel and was subsequently drafted into the German Navy in 1906, serving on a warship stationed in Hamburg. Upon his discharge from the Navy, he acquired a position on a merchant ship and illegally jumped ship in Hoboken, New Jersey in 1911. He describes settling in the Beggars' Boarding House on 5th Street between 1st and 2nd Avenue in the East Village neighborhood of Manhattan, New York, noting the ease with which he found work due to the myriad of small German bakeries in the city. He explains that he worked in many of these bakeries in different parts of the city and moved often in order to live near or in his current workplace. Other topics from his life in the US include the seasonal nature of the baking industry; his time working in Chicago, Illinois; and the development of technology in the baking industry and its role in the obsolescence of many physical laborers.
  - Quartaroni, Tina, 1973 April 11 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 149, Box 48, Reel 162a - 162b)
    Tina Quartaroni was born in Italy and was one of seven children. Her father was a merchant and her mother died when Quartaroni was young. She was the first of her family to immigrate to the United States when she was 21 years old and settled on Mace Avenue in the Bronx, New York. She had a variety of jobs, including dressmaking, packaging Christmas tree lights, and washing and folding laundry.
    This interview was conducted by Norman Newman on April 11, 1973 at an unknown location. Tina Quartaroni is hard to understand due to her heavy accent and distance from the microphone. This interview covers Quartaroni's life in the United States (US) and the many jobs she held in the Bronx, New York. She describes her first few occupations briefly, noting that she transitioned from dressmaking to packaging Christmas tree lights before she found stable work in a laundry. She recounts joining an unspecified laundry workers' union but notes that they didn't strike, and conditions improved after the business was sold. She also describes her husband, including the fact that he rarely worked; his dependence on her income and pension; and their separation when she tired of his idleness and gambling.
    Quartaroni emphasizes the differences between American and Italian Catholic churches, noting that Italian churches tended to be elaborately decorated; that the Italian church fostered a tightly-knit community; and that few people regularly attended Mass in the US.
    Laundry workers |z New York (State) |z New York |v Interviews.
  - Rabinowitz, Hersh, Undated (Box No Master, Box 1, Folder 67)
    Hersh Rabinowitz was born in Ukraine, Russia. He attended a polytechnic institute there for one year before World War I and the Russian Revolution. In 1920 he immigrated to Palestine, where he worked as a metal worker and served as the secretary of an unspecified metal workers' union. He was elected executive secretary of the city council of Tel Aviv and Jaffa in 1921. He and his wife immigrated to the United States in 1923 and settled in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. He received his Bachelor of Science degree in physics and Master of Engineering degree from the City College of New York. He was a member of the Workmen's Circle, Laundry Workers' International Union Local 280, and a founding member of the Federation of Architects, Engineers, Chemists, and Technicians.
    The interviewer, date, and location are unknown. The interview covers Hersh Rabinowitz's life in Palestine and the United States (US), including his work, political activity, and union activity. The beginning of the interview can be found in the recording titled Unidentified Russian man, Rose Gelberg, and Hersh Rabinowitz.
    Rabinowitz recounts being elected executive secretary of city council in Tel Aviv and Jaffa, Palestine in 1921; deciding to leave Palestine; and immigrating to the US in order to continue his education in 1923. He discusses studying English in order to attend night school at the City College of New York and working different jobs while attending college, including laundry worker and engineer. He discusses his union activity, explaining that he was always very active in trade unions, from his time in Palestine in a metal workers' union, as a member of the Laundry Workers' International Union Local 280, and as a founding member of the Federation of Architects, Engineers, Chemists, and Technicians (FAECT) in 1933. He describes the collapse of FAECT in 1951, attributing it to a strike of engineers at the Electric Bond and Share Company (EBASCO) in 1947 and an investigation of FAECT by the House Un-American Activities Committee.
    Rabinowitz discusses the Socialist movement in the US, describing Socialist leaders Morris Hillquit, Meyer London, Norman Thomas, and Eugene V. Debs as giants and explaining that there was no one to succeed them. He discusses, in great detail, reasons for the failure of the Socialist movement, including leaders of powerful labor unions, such as the United Mine Workers and United Auto Workers, suggesting their members invest in the stock market and not participate in political movements as long as their financial interests were met by their employers. He provides reasons that children of immigrants would not make the same sacrifices as their parents and participate in progressive movements.
    See also: Unidentified Russian man, Rose Gelberg, and Hersh Rabinowitz.
    Palestine |x Emigration and immigration |y 20th century.; Engineers |x Labor Unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Federation of Architects, Engineers, Chemists, and Technicians
  - Raia, Anthony, 1974 May 7 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 179, 179a, Box 48, Reel 164a, Box 49, Reel 164b - 164c, Box 1, Folder 68)
    Anthony Raia was born in Lercara Friddi, in the Palermo region of Sicily, Italy in 1904. He immigrated to the United States (US) in 1920, where he worked in multiple industries. He married and had three children. Raia was a member of the Boot and Shoe Workers Union and an unspecified millinery union.
    This interview was conducted by Ginny Yans on May 7, 1974 at Anthony Raia's home in Brooklyn, New York. Throughout the interview, Raia speaks in both Italian and English. Topics of discussion include Raia's family, his emigration from Sicily, Italy, his relationship with his wife and children, his work in the United States (US), and his union involvement. Raia discusses his immigration to the US, including his grandparents immigrating prior to his immigration; sending for his siblings to join him after the death of their father in 1920; and leaving Sicily for economic and social reasons. He recalls meeting his wife after one of her singing performances; having three children with her; feeling proud of his children's accomplishments; believing that men and women need to be treated as equals; and training his wife as a machine operator in a dress factory. He recalls different jobs he held, including work at a piano factory; on submarines in the Brooklyn Navy Yard; for the American Can Company; in shoe manufacturing; and as a part-time actor. He discusses his union involvement, including being a member of the Boot and Shoe Workers Union and an unspecified millinery union; serving on the executive board of the Boot and Shoe Workers Union; being involved in multiple strikes; and being called a Communist because of his involvement with unions.
    Interview fact sheet is available for this interview.
    Millinery workers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Hat trade |x Employees |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.
  - Reid, Edward, 1975 December 12 and 18 (Box Access Cassettes, Cassette 213, 213a-b, Box 49, Reel 165a - 165c, Box 50, Reel 165d)
    Edward Reid was born near Montego Bay, Jamaica on April 22, 1892. He had one older brother. His father worked as a shipwright, traveling aboard ships and performing repairs as necessary, and his mother worked in a laundry. He attended Mt. Zion School in Jamaica until he was 14 years old, when he trained in carpentry. He immigrated to the United States (US) in 1919 and lived with his cousin in Charleston, South Carolina for two years before migrating to New York, New York. He worked as a carpenter for a number of employers, including the Standard Oil Company and the Consolidated Gas Company in Charleston. He joined Local 52 of an unspecified union of black carpenters; the Odd Fellows; and the Freemasons while in the US.